I will call the regular scheduled meeting of my
city council for Tuesday, September 6th, 2022.
Number two, public input, on scheduled personal
premises, we have none.
Three, consent of the State of Oregon,
we have approved item four and five.
Second, six presentation from my
economic development services.
Mr. Shannon, do you have any questions?
Not my strong suit.
Just kidding, just kidding.
Well, first of all, it's great to be here again.
I know I've come before you every quarter.
The main purpose of that is so that we can just kind of
update you on some of the things that we're working on as
an organization.
And we've really been spending a lot of time as
both in a test.
Talking about who we are, where are we going as an
organization?
And it all started even before I came along.
They did a lot of strategic landing sessions.
And among that, see if I can figure out how to do that.
They put together their strategic plan for the rest of
this year and for 2003.
And if you remember Heather Liller came before you,
one of our board members, I think that was back in May.
And she kind of updated you on what those strategic points were
that were going to be the focus for the remainder of this year
and for 2023.
And so we talked a little bit about last time I was here about
what his maids do and how it does that.
And so I'm not going to go over all of that.
I think you also have this in your packet as well.
So I'll try to save some time there and not have to repeat
every word.
But the main things I wanted to update you on is we did finalize
the strategic plan.
We took those six initiatives that Heather told you about back in May
and kind of flush that out a little bit to kind of explain
and define what the board meant by those six items.
So the first one was business retention and expansion.
And obviously that's pretty simple.
That's a main focus for our organization.
I was just doing some research actually over the last couple of
days of last week.
We talked about 70% of all economic growth, business
and industry growth is through business expansion.
And so while a lot of effort is put into attracting new business.
businesses and helping new businesses start, most of the growth that you see in jobs from economic
development actually will come through business and retention and expansion.
So our focus, obviously, is we want to continue to maintain an active business, retention
and expansion committee.
We have that committee in place now.
We'll be updating it, making some changes, because the organization as itself is going
to undergo a few changes, come January.
As you know right now, there's one board in place that oversees both maids and the chamber
of commerce.
Come January, we're going to separate into two different boards.
Still be one location, still working side by side, but we'll have a board that's focused
primarily just on economic development, and one that's going to be focusing on the chamber.
So we're going to be losing board members that may transfer from the current board now to the
chamber side, or they may those that are on the board now that may lean more to chamber
act towards maids information or are maids mission will stay, but there'll be some openings
there that we're going to have to fill and that could change some of our committees, but we
do have a business and retention committee in place.
We want to continue that, and our big thing is we want to get out.
One of the big initiatives we have between now and the end of the year is to spend a lot of
time facing a base with our businesses and we want to make sure we understand what's happening
in their businesses.
We want to know what they need to succeed, what struggles they're having, and how can we help them.
And if we don't have the resources in-house to be able to help them in their growth, then
we're going to go out and find those resources for them.
We want to be a partner in their economic growth, whether it's setting up meetings with people
who can provide specific things, whether it's job training, access to better financing, grant
opportunities, whatever those needs are, we're only going to find out by going out and visiting
with those individuals and then putting that information to work for their benefit.
The second strategic initiative is workforce development, and obviously we all know the importance
of a good workforce.
The city went, he's still posting jobs, right?
I saw an ad on Facebook here this week, or I might have been in the last week whether there's
a number of jobs that were still available here within the city.
That's not uncommon.
There are a lot of businesses in town that are still looking for good employees.
So the question we have to ask is, why are they having such a difficult time finding employees
and how can we solve that problem?
Part of that is by giving to know what their needs are, then we can-
work with all of the resources we have in our, our area to develop a strong workforce because
we have those types of resources available to us.
We have programs in this area that will develop specific training for just about every type
of job opening we have if we can get that information from the businesses and the industry
and relay that to our workforce development agencies and we've got some really good ones in
the area.
So we want to continue to work hand in hand with those folks.
We want to work with the cities, they, county, tribal officers, offices, and we've got
several workforce development programs in our region that we can tap into.
And again, we all know that the success of every organization is going to depend on how
successful we are in finding out what specific training is needed and developing programs to meet
those job needs.
Our next strategic initiatives is obviously collaboration with local city councils, county
government, state government, of course our tribal partners are important and that we're
all in it together.
We're an extension of the city of Miami.
We work with you and for you on certain projects and we love that.
That's a relationship that I think is great for Miami and it's we can foster that same type
of collaborative agreement and effort with all of our other municipalities, commerce,
and sparrow and act in all of them, coming together, working together to bring about economic
development, that's what it's going to take.
What's good for Miami is good for the county and if it's good for someone else in the county,
trust me, Miami will benefit from that.
So we want to continue those relationships, communications important.
We want to meet with our tribal leaders on a regular basis, but when I will see each other
at the inner tribal council meetings and visit, so we need to continue that.
There's the inner tribal, we need to start going to the county commissioners meetings.
That's our next step.
We want to go before the Miami City Council meeting on a regular basis, not just for my quarterly
report.
And I hope you've seen that we've already started that process and you'll see me here at Council
meetings, not because I'm on the agenda, but mainly because I just want to stay informed
of what's going on within the city, because there may be some opportunities for me to help.
And that's what we want to do.
We want to be a partner in economic development and of course, that same offer extends to all
of our area municipalities, not just the city of Miami.
Our fourth strategic initiative is revenue growth, and we have to help grow our economy.
But we also have to, as an organization, we need to grow our own funds.
It means there's no number that any organization we have, we want to make sure that we're
putting those resources to the best and most efficient use possible.
How do we create more jobs?
How can we improve training to better input those seeding jobs to find new jobs?
To do that.
We're no different from anyone.
So we have to do that.
We can do that for several different ways.
We can do that throughout the evolving world program, in which we take money, we have,
moment to a business that helps us start up or help us expand or hopefully attract a new
company to the area.
And they return pay us back within years.
We had a 54,000 square foot spent building that we need to put to good use.
We've been working all day long about the decisions to create that spend building, but the
reality is that it's done, it's there.
And we need to do so.
We can't just have that huge investment sitting there collecting stuff.
You can sell it.
We need to see it.
We need to get some jobs.
We do that.
We continue to work with our partners.
That revenue will come off this.
Initiative is marketing and branding, which is nothing more than the face of the way
to say we need to do better jobs and telling them the things.
How do we let people know?
So our purpose has been to develop an internal and external marketing strategy.
The first thing we've learned there was put together in this strategic.
That's the first two.
Yeah.
That's a tool that as we go out, I go out.
And I meet with all of the businesses of industry in our area.
I'm going to bring that copy of our strategic plan with me as a tool to show that each of
the things that are important to us.
Every decision that we make as an organization should come back to the six initiatives.
If it doesn't, that's no different, probably than what we're getting ready to do.
Oh, it's probably not.
It's something like one.
I'm very old.
It's strategic.
It's a city of Lyama.
And when he does, he's going to challenge you to say that.
Everything we do, or you do, we'll be full.
It needs to revert back to that plan.
If it doesn't, we're working right now.
Actually, this is done.
It's not live yet.
I finished it.
Right.
haven't gone by and whether yet, you have a new website.
That address is building my amount, OK, doctor.
So it should go live here in the next few days.
Definitely, by the end of the week.
But that will be another tool that we can use.
It's got a modern cool weatheration on it.
It is not complete.
As an unfinished final product, we can constantly
be added to it and upgrade it.
But there's enough there now to give this go.
It also has a complete section on getting started, which is basically a nod for anyone
out there who's willing to start their own business.
It will walk you through the process.
Of course, we want to develop a new logo tag around and a sense of who
we are working on that, or at least the highest of our priorities.
But it's something we think we need to do to tell people, we're going to have
a new business.
We put a lot of effort into helping our current business.
It's the need to show them that most of the growth we're going to see is going to come
from our existing business.
That doesn't mean we want to set up a lot of time and effort into attracting new business.
We need to highlight what the region has to offer and we need to have some positive things.
We sit here all night long and talk about some of the negatives and we know it goes
long.
But we do have some positives.
The thing is that we had an outside tell us, I know people, this is a hard concept to
grasp.
It's for just outside of this perspective, we just have to talk about what we're going to say.
We're looking at the whole of primarily, and I am a homeless, specifically, was the low cost.
Can you say that one more time?
No, it was the true story.
It was the true story.
Whether we can assist them, or we can be some joint projects,
those public private collaborative efforts are huge for economic development.
And we need to see what they have to say.
See what their needs are.
And we need to tell them we need help.
We need to do that.
We need to make some positive things happen.
And then of course, another way we can try to attract these businesses,
but in fact, building public loan funds is extremely underutilized.
And to assist businesses to start, to expand, or to move to buy a local home,
which is easy to come.
We necessarily need to use this company.
It's all something more important.
That's the one in the process.
Yeah.
You are job.
Just close to someone we already have.
You know that's our normal one prior.
We're still going to try to do business.
New business and industry adds to our culture,
adds to the growth,
and stability of our economy.
We're going to do too many customers from the city of Miami,
and it helps with the tax base.
And so just in case you don't remember,
who makes up on her or on directors,
and this will change, you know, January 1.
But as of right now, these are our more of directors.
You can see, you've got lower, low grease,
and an anti-dition of the city of Miami.
We're going to do it all the way.
My home number and the rest,
or a whole lot of things that are going to be
in a single word,
you'd be here for an hour.
But I do appreciate the opportunity to come before you and visit with you.
I always enjoy coming for the city council.
We'll probably be back here for too much longer.
Just to update you on a completely different topic.
And that's our veteran's hunt that's coming up.
You guys at the city of Miami has always been very supportive of us,
and drafting proclamations for our hunters.
We've already sent that information in.
I believe Molly was here.
And Melissa, have that information.
But we're excited about doing another hunt.
We'd love to have you participate,
but we'll share more information on that at another time.
Can I answer any questions?
Yes, sir.
I don't know.
When is the inception of Maine?
Okay.
So, Maine's session goes back to mid-AIDS.
Right after the closure of good.
five, eight, six.
I'll pick if you think things have been,
there's not one that can scale.
Throughout its course, I'll put it up five or six.
I think, and I say that,
that's looking at the entire longevity.
I think there are a lot of peaks and valleys
in the, there are moments in there where they were very hot.
And there are moments probably when they're going to slide,
as they would have liked it.
But the beauty of that is, you keep plugging away.
If you cannot solve every economic development issue,
in the city of Miami, or all of the county,
you wouldn't get so long-term to keep that in mind.
Communication bonds open, people willingness to work,
then those numbers should only go up.
I just got curious to the sense that,
what you've presented sounded like as a whole week.
Well, you know, there's been some turnover,
there have been some changes, there have been some issues.
Some of them, not so good.
So, we're still trying to recover from that.
And so, it is time for a new approach.
It is time for a new attitude.
It's time to look to new solutions to all the problems.
And that's what we're going to try to do with health.
People like, I'll say, in a wrap up,
to go over his mayor, I hope that he may have helped.
And these are my work.
I didn't feel like Major was given the job done for us.
I tried to force a few things.
And then we didn't get some more changes to done.
He started a little bit.
It would be a little more back to the end,
which he said about.
But I think we're in a Shannon on Gisiting Life.
And Gisiting has to remove the given another shot,
because he didn't happen.
Despite building is a kill, he's healed for all of us.
I mean, that was something that was dreamed up by somebody else.
What was that, Bill?
I was six years ago, right?
I was mad at him.
He was built as a babysitter.
Yes.
I didn't have to sleep.
So I don't know what's going on.
I just don't know if all of your question comes to me.
You have a tool by which you know that you're in someone else.
You're next to hot-of-wall the agenda actually, but this is a tool that we work for
the EU.
So you have something that you have.
You have this strategic initiative, which you can hold every decision we make to
and then you actually have a contraction of agreement with the city of Miami and
it's a lot of some of the things that were responsible.
Any strange things?
The mayor must have that one.
I must have that.
I must have that one.
I mean, what if you play on it?
Is trying to sell it?
Is trying to lease it?
The matter is trying to lease up with it?
Our first part already would be to sell it.
That would be our numbers.
How was it?
I think it was a pitful time.
So that's our main part.
It'll be a lot better.
We'll compare these here and to a lease agreement.
They want you to lease the facility.
Thank you for the good news.
Thank you for getting some jobs.
And we can generate some revenue on that.
The doctor talked first part of it is to sell second part of it.
And I'll say too that before Shannon took over, we had a pretty good lead on the company
that wanted the building.
We actually met with them at the end of March.
And they drug us along and drug us along to last week.
And I got a phone call that said they know an owner needed the building.
They're out because they're supply chain picked up.
And they were getting their stuff overseas.
They wouldn't expect them.
And that was when we thought we were really going to get several times.
They drug us along for several months.
And I think those opportunities came on a couple times.
And for some reason or another, it didn't happen.
And I'll say that the building sits at the base of it.
They're probably just changing.
Right.
One thing.
The economy change.
The most supply line issues they were having.
You used up.
They no longer added.
And we got a problem.
We got a couple of reasons.
And the guy when he told me that they weren't a dirty said it wasn't anything we did.
That we were great.
That they loved the people they dealt with.
They've retreated fairly.
They've just the supply chain changed for them.
That that made them change their direction.
So.
And because once you haven't took over.
We kind of turned that over to him because before we didn't have anybody.
So we were all trying to handle it, but we turned it over to Shannon, and so now it's his baby.
But...
I think sometimes two people don't realize how difficult bringing a new business, a new company here really is.
I'm one of those people.
I thought it would be really easy, you know, no big deal, but it's a little tougher than what a lot of people think, because of what they're looking for.
Sometimes...
...and that's a lot of people.
I don't want to have our killer heels as housing.
We just don't have the housing for people to move here.
And so I know that's something we've looked at too, and talk to people about housing,
because we need places for people to move.
Something I think that's exciting, that we've...
...I don't believe we've seen before in the past that I think it would be different with Shannon.
Is we actually have...
...when you read that sign, my area, economic development, it's not my image, my area.
And we've got commerce, fairly in, after all coming together,
and wanting to start meeting on a regular basis, and pulling on resources, and what that allows Shannon to do
is it gives him a better workforce to market.
So instead of just going and saying, I've got this one workforce, he can go and say,
I've got this regional workforce, and it helps him when he's filling out those beds,
and responding to him gives him more resources to put on there, and it makes us more attractive.
Thank you.
I'm seven.
Economic development agreement with Marna.
Area economic development service.
So this is the agreement that Shannon was just talking about.
It's an annual agreement.
This one is very much similar to last year's agreement with one major exception.
And that is also something Shannon mentioned.
Come January, they're splitting the maids and the chamber on their end of the deal.
Last year's contract was between a city and maids and the chamber.
So this is just with maids.
They will be the ones that will be directly benefited from the agreement.
Now it's understood that the chamber will still stay in the same building.
They'll still indirectly get some benefits from it.
But this agreement is just between maids and maids.
Other than that it's essentially the same agreement as what we've had in the past.
So this is the same dollar amount as last year.
Yes.
And the utility credit is the same.
I think it asks this question last year, but it is.
City Miami, the only one.
That's helping fund maids.
And for the first time we've started having conversations with the other communities.
And they've asked how could they participate.
The revolving loan fund is that substantial or is that something that you're working towards to.
I mean, I mean the fund to get out of it.
No last year, a couple of us had questions.
It's kind of hard to improve $66,000.
It's like made this so secret to it.
They tell accounts on nothing or what they work on.
You're so vague and everything that is said that it's
hard for me to vote yes to stay on board with you guys when.
Hi, they might, but I don't see nothing progress.
We don't know what's in the works, we don't know, we can't vary.
Right, that's what the previous lady told us to and she never brought
an epintivist at all.
We don't know what brings us up to you.
If they take me along, trust me.
We're getting there.
If you want to be your pink question, you just can't...
The sit takes about the company close with the, unless they didn't get a list.
Yeah, no, because he recently, within the last three, four months, so I'm going to wait for it.
This is coming in, this is coming in.
I've seen nothing coming in.
And there are some things that this company is still vacant.
They can't talk about it.
So I'm going to talk to you because there are some things that are on it.
I'll be happy to share that.
That doesn't have to be shared with.
And then, also, I would add, don't forget, one of the significant initiatives that
Mays has his business retention and expansion.
You're not going to see business retention unless somebody leaves.
And then that tells you is not working.
The business retention is all of the effort that they put in there,
meeting with all of our existing manufacturers, understanding their needs,
and what their, their needing workforce wise, communicating between the state and those entities.
So there's a lot of effort that's put into that in a lot of time and energy that goes into.
And I've seen, first hand, the relationships that Shannon's already having to
develop and that were there before with a lot of our local industry.
And I think part of that too would be going out and, and, and,
actually, or maybe two of you.
So local industry and find out what their opinion is.
I think that's something we need to continue to.
And we talk to any of our local, so you talk about expansion and retention.
So we talk to any of our local businesses that are looking to expand.
All the time.
Maybe to, to take this spec moment.
Yes.
Yeah.
Yep.
Yes.
It, it, it, it, it really comes up quite a bit.
I mean, I've met with, I don't know how many now local, a handful, locally,
that I've wanted to look at it and it usually goes on for weeks at a time.
The engineers get involved and it's, kind of, quote,
seller that needs to be, but isn't.
There's, well, that hasn't really kept any of them from saying that we were very competitive.
So luckily, I think we're still in the running.
It's just going to take the right combination.
I think, too, right now, one of the pluses for that building is,
where it would cost a build it now.
Yeah.
That's what it meant.
That.
I'll make a motion.
I'll say, Brad, did a question.
I'll ask your questions, everybody here.
I just wanted to say something.
Well, do you want to ask any questions about now?
I mean.
Now, and the reason why I say that is,
because I know very little about it,
or to the background with it.
But this is probably not going to be a subject
that could come up in executive session.
But the questions probably need to be in open meeting.
So this is a time to ask questions.
If everybody else looks like it's got to go now.
So for what it's going to happen?
Yeah, this is something that we've been very involved with.
Since since I got here, this is one of the things that
I had more than quite a bit about.
I hadn't developed.
You know, what's happening?
What's happening?
Well, I have one of the things that I had more
than quite a bit about.
I hadn't developed.
Well, the economic development in the municipal level
in the state level, over here.
And I'd say there was some progress in that.
There was some back, method of work.
You can go down the other.
I've been through down very much in process with him.
The rebandle of my angel.
So we created a fiscal subject committee.
Of which myself had her low-ered
and Dr. Stafford said on.
And so we've been continuing to provide additional oversight
in other financials and making recommendations
to the board itself and to the executive team.
And I would tell you from what I found out.
The services they're providing are good and are going up, and we continue to be very optimistic
because we're setting a pretty high bar as a board, and we're looking at and are in the
process of identifying metrics so we can measure performance a little more closely, because
to Duane's point sometimes it's difficult because you can't get into all the details, even
as a board, we don't get into a lot of the, sometimes the, too many details.
Because of the confidentiality issues, so we're capturing metrics that we can track.
That being said, I would also tell you, this is one of the things you get out of it
exactly what you put into it.
So the more that a community invests into economic development programs, the more opportunity
for return that it has.
And I would tell you, from everything that I've learned since I've been here, we're scraping
the bottom of the barrel.
We are absolutely, when you compare us to other growing communities like Clair Mournawasso and
others, and have really done well since 1986, we are absolutely paying a fraction of what
they put into their community for economic development.
So I would say that's why this number doesn't, doesn't offend me or surprise me that what
they're asking for.
So I would tell you all from my seat, which is different from yours, because I'm not voting
on it, but I feel comfortable with this number and what I've been able to see.
So when you talk about the changing of the boards and new things come out, is it feasible
that a council person set on this board?
On one of those boards?
I don't see why not.
There's going to be a lot of positions.
Right.
So there's the mayor in the city manager now.
Because they meet for like three hours sometimes.
And I mean, my work didn't like that very well.
So every day.
And it's in the middle of the day too, so I didn't feel like I could do it and do it
adequately.
So we're talking about adding quite a few spots.
So when we split these boards up, they combined them back and I think 2013-16 something like that.
And thought it would provide some efficiencies, and to be honest, they've all decided it
did not work.
And so as we've been through this process, trying to really identify where we think we could
see improvements, this is one of the areas that we said we just don't have enough representation
especially for the chamber side.
The chamber side ought to be something that's driven by our local businesses.
And although we have some business owners on the board today, there's only a few.
And it really ought to be made up of a bunch because they ought to be the driving force behind
that.
And so we'll be adding quite a-
bit of positions on the chamber side probably not so many on the
made side from what I believe. I probably will continue to focus on
mates on that area economic development and so that may leave Amanda then to
focus on more of the chamber side which is more of an if there's a memory of
this board that wants that seat. I can go to Amanda and say I we've got a
board member that wants that seat and I'm sure it won't hurt her feelings any.
She said a lot of do anyway so I can appoint one of you guys off to see how it all works and
so if there's somebody that can be there but I can say sometimes it's three hours in a
middle of the day so I know I can't. We're trying to speed those up. That's part of
the reason we started the fiscal subcommittee. But to delaying this point earlier
and the chance point about the stuff we've heard that's coming that hadn't
started yet. I can see why the confidence you out is big because I know the
things the way we're talking about they are coming. But they've changed sites three or four
times and some of them can't get their supplies here so it's not taking 11 months to
build their building. Can they come in to close and talk about it.
Executive on on stuff like that. One of the things. Not today. Not today.
So an executive session for the state rules. There's only a handful of things that
allow. So economic development is one of them so we just have to make sure that
you are broad enough yet restricted in that if we're going to stay within the parameters of
what the state law allows. But if you're talking about meeting with potential
businesses. I'm that like half-shan and come in and talk to us not telling you what's going
on. If it was a general conversation probably not. If it was a specific
confidentiality even if he shared it on the group that was considered confidential
and so it would still breach. So the challenge that he has is he's got businesses
that he's dealing with that are sometimes looking at making major you know hundreds of thousands
of dollars of investment if not millions of dollars in investments. And if that information gets
out it jeopardizes their project completely. It could drive the cost up if somebody finds out
a competitor finds out and he said wait. I want to go and get in there quicker. I want to make
a different offer. I want to undercut them. Then that creates a significant liability.
If we should own our own property owners.
Well, they find out.
Yes.
They're property triples and valuables.
It's tough.
Any other questions?
We really just can't resolve the urge in.
And that's where we've kind of been before.
Yes.
The same place last year.
But we've got somebody new, leading that now.
And I think we probably ought to give him the chance.
My opinion is we need to give Shannon a chance.
The real tough position that you're in is you have to kind of trust what's being put
up for you that good things are happening because the only alternative is to not fund
maids.
And then maids, financially, would become unmanaged for them.
They wouldn't have enough funds to operate.
Which means they would go away.
Which means what you're risking is the existing manufacturers and entities say, and this is not a
town.
I want to do business because they don't even support us.
Business retention and expansion opportunities to evades.
And so you wouldn't really know that not funding them had a negative impact.
Until the negative impact happened.
So it's kind of a tough spot.
Again.
I will read your motion.
Second.
Hi.
I'm great.
Budget amendment 23.
That's your five general fund grant capital improvement project.
All right.
Thank you again.
Again after the end of the year.
We read the deterioration over for these three funds.
This is the general fund.
Capital improvement fund in the grant fund.
We are just in those estimated carryovers to actual carryovers.
The general fund had a couple of purchase orders that did not get fulfilled.
Facilities was doing carpet upstairs.
They couldn't get that done before the end of the year.
They need to re-encumber those funds.
HR is doing a salary study and revising the personnel policy that they need to finish up.
They didn't get finished before the end of the year.
We have two capital improvement projects that need to be re-encumbered.
One is a watchguard camera system for the police department.
And the other one is the emergency generator for the Civic Center.
Grant fund.
They'll have specific parts orders that we're re-encumbering but we're allowing each department to spin.
carry over that they have with them at the park. You go ahead and answer any questions.
Good motion. We have proof.
Thank you, Mike.
Number nine, contract with Mom Public Schools to provide three school resource officers for the
223 school year, $133,000 reimbursement.
This is our annual contract with Mom Public Schools. We provide three school resource officers to work
the schools of the school system. They pay approximately 75% of that salary, which is the
nine months during school, and that's a hundred and fifty three thousand this year, and we
amend that every year after the contract negotiation with the large, just reflecting the
salaries. They've been in the schools now for about 15 years, a great partnership, and our officer
do is to manage the job as schools.
Any questions for Chief?
I'll make the motion to approve.
All right.
10, renewal of following annual contracts of the fiscal year 223.
These are from the same ones in the MSUA, the Booth and Booth and Booth electric, HK electric, the Winston-Plombing,
Konell and Teeter and Teeter's Paving.
Motion to approve.
All right.
11. Warbed C22-44 in the amount of $38,358 to stay in tech LLC for removal of underground storage tanks,
associated piping pumps, canopy at 1030 East Southwest, which was big datties.
The pre-contracting position upon the submission of required contract documents and approved
city manager is doesn't need to sign notice to seek.
Yes. So this is big datties that we purchased through the FEMA grant and a part of that,
not a part of the FEMA grant, but part of our responsibility in owning the property now is to remove
the underground storage tanks and the canopy in the fuel pumps and all of them.
those. We have to have a special contractor do that, that is licensed to do that type of remove
removal. And that's, we put that out to bid. We received one bid back on the project,
which is in your, is in your packet.
Just got one bid to the session specialized.
Well, you sent it out to several. You never know why some people bid and some people don't.
Do you have anybody local that does this kind of stuff?
No.
I will note that the $9,232 that is for the removal transport and disposal of the fluid found in the tanks.
This bidter actually went out and measured it at the time that he submitted his bid.
That dollar amount could fluctuate depending on if there's more or less fluid in those tanks at the time that it's removed.
Is there a cap on how much it looks like?
Well, I'd have to come back.
Thanks.
As far as what we would pay for it, I would have to come back to you guys with a change order.
I know like Chris had said on some of our bid, the cap was 10% for a change rate.
I didn't know if there was something like that on this or not.
On this one too.
This is coming out of the demo fund.
The grant you've already received.
No, this isn't funded by the grant.
The property was part of the grant.
But our removal of the tanks is the city's responsibility as owning the property.
FEMA in this type of grant is not concerned with anything underground.
It's just anything above ground.
I'm not just going to get a chance of building.
I don't want to know what he said.
It was interesting.
Okay.
When are they playing out doing this work?
Well, I don't have a specific data depends on when we issue the.
We'll issue the notice to proceed.
I can get back to you on that date because he'll have to get his.
There's a performance bond and all of that stuff that he'll have to get.
Will be this year.
Oh yeah.
I'll make a motion to approve.
Hi.
Thank you, Christine.
I'll you're staying.
Yep.
Number 12 discussion concerning potential fee waivers for my
Public Schools construction projects.
So from time to time, the MIMA Public Schools has construction projects.
And the difference a construction project is a building project not just a
mechanical electric or plumbing project that regular maintenance that the schools
have to do.
We have two construction projects that we've gotten planned submitted on for
MIMA Public Schools.
One is for physical education building at the high school, which is a
6,000 square foot addition to the high school.
The other is a renovation and addition for MIMA Public Schools
Administration at their what's going to be their new location over by
Nichols.
And that's a 5,100 square foot addition.
So from time to time, they have these projects in the school
bond project.
We waved all of the building and permit fees associated with the school
bond projects.
These are separate.
So we wanted to find out from the council what direction you would
want to take on these types of construction projects in the future.
If it's something that you want to see each one of them and us come back
every time we have a construction project like this to do a fee
waiver.
We can do that.
If you have the mindset of any type of building construction project that the
school system might do, we want to support them by waving the permit
inspection fees.
We can come back with the resolution doing that also.
I think that's how it should be.
We should wave all fees.
Travis gave me an estimate just so you would know on these two projects.
We're talking about about 1,500 dollars on each of those for building permit
and inspection fees.
It doesn't wave doing the inspections and getting the permits.
It just waves the fees we charge for them.
I think I agree with the one.
I think it's important for the city to be a good partner with our school system
and support their efforts.
Because you got good school system.
You got good buildings.
You got good facilities.
It's going to drop people here.
A lot of companies are looking to come and relocate.
They look at your school.
I think it's important for us to be a good partner with them.
So I think I'm understanding that you guys would like for us to come back with a
resolution to wave building and permit fees on building
construction projects for the school.
system. Okay, we can do that.
Thank you, Christy. 13 other new business, which is the
residents is posting this agenda. 14 staff reports, 15 mayor
council community announcements. I want to say the
rodeo was outstanding. Once again, Bobby Carter has
teamed a great job with that. Again, rodeo of the year for
association. I talked to the announcer after the last night.
I ran into him and they came for coming and he does a
great job. And he told me that this was the best
rodeo they do all year. And he said, I mean, not even
close. And he said, we do some pro rodeos. And this
rodeo is better. So I mean, that was a huge statement for
me. And if you were out there Saturday night and you saw
this dance, I heard and I didn't hear this myself. I heard
this from someone else that there was actually people asking for
their money back because they couldn't find a seat. That's a
good problem to have. So we may have to get some more stands or something.
But you had people not been able to find a seat because it was so
full. Of course Friday was a little bit lighter because you're
your first night of high school football. So a little bit lighter
in Friday, about those. Everybody is back. A lot of people there.
Saturday night we also had a gigantic event at Buffalo runs. So
that took that took some people out. If we had about 6,000
people had our pay or a place. So I mean you had two events going on
and they were both big. So I thought it was a big statement for
that guy to say that there was even pro rodeos that this rodeo
was better than and then I ran into caught a highsmith at
on Sunday and I was shocked by this statement. He said this was the first time he'd ever been
in the modern radio because he always goes, if they need the radio because he grew up going
to the need of the radio and he said this was the first time I went to my Amos and he said
I was blown away at how good it was. He said it blows beneath his away. So actually there's
this four nights. I think there were those four nights where ours is three, I guess with Thursday,
it was like that. But anyway, Bobby and his crew do a good job and I think he's going to come
during next meeting and give us an update on the radio. So it was great that he did a good job.
So I thought he had taken some numbers. I don't know. He may have that. I don't know.
But I think they said that was sorry, not they believe was the second largest crowd they remember at I'm just gonna go with this
If you guys don't have anything
So 16 city manager communications
Then all right, so 17 the gentleman and I'm going to end up the executive session